# **Esaa Yamini**

Austin, TX 78701

Phone: 512.954.3267 | Email: esaa.yamini@gmail.com LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/esaa-yamini-8864227 Github: https://eyamini.github.io/

### **Summary**

Big data professional. Fifteen years combined leadership experience in intelligence analysis, big data architecture, data science, developing big data programs, and military intelligence. Top Secret/SCI clearance.

Multidisciplined leader and Army Reserve Officer with extensive experience leading large teams (100+) to collect, analyze, and produce tangible information for senior decision makers. Data inspired subject matter expert with entrepreneurial spirit and passion for clear, concise, actionable information.

#### **Technical Skills**

#### **Tools**

Python, Scala, R, Pandas, Tableau, Matplotlib, NumPy, Hadoop, Spark, Bootstrap, Beautiful Soup, Cloud ETL, Swift, NLP, and JavaScript **Databases** 

US Air Force's ELICSAR Big Data Platform (BDP), PostgreSQL, Extract-Transform-Load (ETL), MongoDB

# **Relevant Experience**

Data Scientist/Architect (Team Lead)

2020 - Present

B.E.A.T. LLC

San Antonio, TX

Leads big data team in support of U.S. Air Force Cyber Command. Responsible for planning, developing, implementation, documentation, and maintenance of the first big data platform hosted on a classified network. Developed analytic software (in Scala) capable of searching the BDP for indicators of compromise. Authored several developer and big data architecture manuals for data architects, developers, and data scientists to replicate achievements.

#### **Intelligence Officer (O4 Major)**

2005 - Present

#### **U.S. Army Reserves**

Austin, TX

Senior intelligence officer with experience in leadership roles at all Army organizational levels. Commanded a military intelligence unit sized over 110 personnel. Delivered intelligence briefings to combined civilian and military audiences. Drafted complex intelligence products for unit missions with supporting briefings using data science tools such as Palantir, Query Tree, M3, and Pathfinder. Trained, supervised, and managed an intelligence unit responsible for intelligence production for United States Southern Command (USSOUTHCOM).

## **Additional Experience**

# **Senior Intelligence Analyst (multiple)**

2006 - 2012

#### Booz Allen Hamilton, CACI, Athena, & HSA

Charlottesville, VA; San Antonio, TX; & Afghanistan Leveraged big data resources to generate and brief simplified, easy to process, intelligence products. Prepared Biometric Intelligence Analysis Reports (BIARS) in support of deployed Intelligence Fusion Teams. Utilized interagency intelligence databases to compile comprehensive intelligence products. Led civilian intelligence teams in Afghanistan.

#### **Education**

#### Data Analysis and Visualization: University of Texas

Austin, TX

Six-month certificate granting program focused on technical programming in Python, R, JavaScript, SQL Databases, Tableau, NLP, Pandas, Hadoop, Spark, Big Data, MongoDB, & Machine Learning.

Advanced Military Intelligence: U.S. Army Intelligence Center Fort Huachuca, AZ 2005-2017, All Source Intelligence.

Bachelor's Degree: Indiana University South Bend, IN 2001-2005, Psychology.